Hello and welcome to an introductory
organic video focusing on
addition reactions of alkenes.
So in this video, we're gonna go
through all the different types of
addition reactions that you typically
see in the introductory organic
course, focusing first on alkenes.
The whole idea about this with addition is
that we are going to be adding something,
but one way for us to be able to look
at this reaction is imagine whenever we
have an Quin, how it has the double bond.
Well, we want to imagine that
double bond as a set of doors that
we're gonna be opening up to add
our different components to it.
So when I say open the cabinet doors, we
want to be able to redraw our structure
and to add our components to it.
So with all these different reactions,
the big thing about them is generally the
carbon structure always stays the same.
Uh, we just bring along all the
little hydrogens and components.
Now one other thing.
What are we exactly looking at?
What are we adding?
Well, in this particular reaction,
I'm showing just X as a species.
It doesn't necessarily matter what it is.
We are adding X.
Now, as I mentioned, we are opening
up the cabinet door so that double
bond opens and we are going to be
adding an X species to both sides.
So we have X on the left
and then X on the right.
And that's the whole idea is
we're opening up the door and
then adding different species.
So we're gonna go through a bunch
of different reactions to understand
that when you have this, we are always
gonna be starting with an alkene
on the left, making an alkane as a
product, that we go from that double
bond CC to a single bonded C over here.
And the whole idea is that when we
write this, we're gonna be adding two
components together to make one product.
So we go from two things.
Down to one product in the end.
So let's take a look
at our first reaction.
So addition reactions generally
always have in the name what we
are adding for this first reaction.
We have hydrogenation, which
is all about adding hydrogen.
We can see that directly
in the name hydrogen.
So with this one, how is it written?
Well, what we can see is here.
Each two is written on top of our
reaction arrow, letting you know this
is what we're going to be adding.
Most of these reactions will have a
catalyst or, uh, in this one specific for
hydrogenation, and it's written below.
The arrow let you know that there
is a catalyst that is present in
order for the reaction to happen.
Now, as I mentioned before, this entire
reaction is gonna be happening where
we're opening up those double doors.
So I'm gonna just kind of draw that, that
double bond and just highlight where the
doors are, where they're gonna be opening.
So first thing that we're gonna be doing
is re-drawing our structure so we have
that, those three individual carbons,
and then we're gonna be opening up the
double door and they don't necessarily
have to be pointing the same direction.
We are opening it to show that
we are going to be adding a
hydrogen to each component.
So whenever we have H2, that is
telling you that we have a hydrogen
being added to both sides of the
double bond as we are opening that up.
So as we can see, one gets, one
hydrogen gets added on, one carbon,
one on the other, which is where our
locations of our double bond were.
We add a hydrogen to both parts.
Let's try another example.
So in fact, we have multiple, so if we are
to do these individual reactions, the same
idea is we redraw the carbon structure.
So we'll redraw our shape
here for the first structure.
And what we are gonna be
doing is we're opening up the
location of the double bond.
So the double bond here is on
carbon two, and then carbon three.
So we open it up there and
we're gonna be adding a hydrogen
onto each individual part.
Same thing with the next chain.
Uh, with this ring structure, we're going
to draw our ring, we're going to open up
the double bond, and we'll add a hydrogen
to each part so we can see that we're
going from two products down to one.
Even with this last example, we'll redraw.
The carbon framework.
We'll even put the halogen in the bromine
and the chlorine, and it's the same idea,
is that we are going to be opening up
that double bond and just highlighting
all these, just so we can see it.
We're gonna open that up and put a
hydrogen on each individual part to
show how the doors are opening, right?
We're adding a car, adding our group
onto the carbons, participating.
In the double bond.
So whichever structure we're looking
at, whether it's the first one, right?
We have carbon number two,
and then carbon number three.
Those are going to be
participating in that opening.
Let's go onto our next reaction.
Our next reaction type is
Halogenation, and from this one you
can see the same general premise.
It gives you the name inside
of saying -ation, right?
We're adding something.
So in this case, we're adding a halogen.
So halogen can be chlorine,
flourine, iodine, bromine any
of those individual species.
So usually we denote that with the
letter X and that can represent
any of these major halogens.
So for this one, it's gonna follow
the same idea of hydrogenation.
We open up the double bond and
we will have a group on each
of those individual carbons.
So just to kind of label
those carbons, right?
So we have one carbon here in red,
the other one in red as well, and
we can really illustrate that that
is what's going to be opening.
So we will redraw our structure.
And we are going to open
up the double bonds.
So we'll put one on carbon
one, one on carbon two.
And being that we're adding
chlorines, there will be a Cl
on each individual structure.
Um, so we're adding to each part
and it might be a common thing
where you even might have to name
it and go through naming rules or
an even go farther so this video.
We're just gonna particularly show.
Is how we can add these little parts.
And if you want to, you can always try
to clean up your structure as well.
So for example, we can show that,
okay, we're adding our little
chlorine, chlorine with the methyl
group, so it looks a little bit more
like a correct geometry as well.
Let's try and let's try some more.
So with these particular
geometries, same idea.
We're going to be copying
down the main structure.
So here we have our chain.
And as before, like I mentioned,
we have our double bond.
So this is our door that
we're gonna be opening.
So we will add one on this carbon and
then one on the next carbon to show.
Okay, we open the door and we're
adding a bromine to each portion.
For the next one, we are adding
iodine to our cyclohexene.
So in this case, what we're going to be
doing is we are going to be adding our
cyclohexene to our double bond here.
We are going to be opening up that
structure and then writing an iodine
on each portion of this species.
And notice how it went from an alkene
to an a cycloalkane with halides on it.
So it's an alkyl halide.
That we're changing the
functional group along with it.
So the carbon chain always stays the same
as the functional group that is changing.
So same thing with this last example.
We are gonna be opening
up our double bond.
We will leave our bromine and our
chlorine that was originally there, and
we're gonna be adding chlorines to each
individual part of the double bond.
So we're gonna open up those
doors and add our pieces.
And this is the whole idea
with these types of reactions
that involve the same species.
So we have H2 or F2 or Cl2
they all have that
diatomic characteristic.
Now let's go into something
that is not a diatomic and is
more of a heterogeneous species.
So hydro halogenation is
when you add a hydrogen.
And a halogen, meaning we have two
different species, but it's still gonna
be following the same general idea.
We're gonna be adding both components.
However, one thing you're gonna
quickly realize is, well, if I'm
adding two pieces, so we have, we're
gonna be adding a hydrogen, um,
and why don't we color code these?
So let's say if we add a hydrogen in
blue and we'll add a bromine in red.
Well, the same idea is that we're gonna
be opening up the double bond, however,
what side do you put each species on?
Because if we are to draw this
structure, we can see that.
All right.
Well, we'll have one species where
we can put the hydrogen, let's
say, or the bromine, let's say on
the left, hydrogen on the right.
And if we were to redraw
that, we could also write it.
Where I could have hydrogen on
the left and bromine on the right.
Now the question is,
well, which one is true?
We have two different options of products.
So what we actually have to do
is we have to be able to predict
the correct or the major product
that is formed within a reaction.
So how exactly do we do that?
Well, we're going to go
off the following rule.
The following rule is all about,
it's called Markovnikov's rule.
This is one, it's one of our
few rules that we come across
in introductory organic, which
is a a scary long Russian name.
So with Markovnikov's rule, the
whole idea behind it is that
hydrogen wants to bond near hydrogen.
So the way I like to view it is
that hydrogen wants to make more
friends that are just like hydrogen.
Hydrogen is a social butterfly that
likes to bond to another species.
So if we have our example from before,
well, we had two different products.
How did we know which
one is the major species?
So what it comes down to is
going to our original reactant.
So if we go to this reactant, we
are looking at the double bond.
And like I mentioned, hydrogen
wants to bond near more hydrogens.
So what we're gonna do is we're
gonna look at both carbons, the
one on the left and the one on
the right and count our hydrogens.
So how exactly do we do that?
Well, let's take a look.
So if I'm on the carbon right
here, How exactly do I go
about trying to count carbons?
And let's pick a different color
other than R, other than yellow.
So let's redraw that.
So if we have, let's say our carbon
right here, how can we decide that?
Well, we have one bond here, two bonds.
And then three bonds
all around this carbon.
So how much room is there for hydrogen?
Well, we can fit a total of one
more hydrogen on this carbon.
Now if we look at the other carbon,
which I'll draw in purple here.
Well, what can we do
if we zoom in on that?
How many bonds are around
that particular carbon?
Well, same idea as before.
We're going to count the number
of bonds it currently has, and
we can see that we have one.
We have two for our double bond,
three and four for the single bond.
So is there any room for hydrogen?
And if you remember, carbon
can bond up to four things.
It already has all four bonds.
So for this one, well, we have
zero hydrogens on this carbon.
We have zero on this side and then
we have one hydrogen on the left.
So what is gonna happen is hydrogen
wants to be with other hydrogens.
So the correct structure is gonna be this
bottom one, which showed that hydrogen
wants to be with its fellow hydrogens.
So both of them are gonna be there.
It is happy it has its friend.
So this is what we refer
to as the major product.
When it comes to the markovnikov
type of reaction, let's look at
some further examples of this.
With this example, we're gonna be taking
the following alkane and adding HCl to it.
So what do we have to exactly do?
Well, it's the same idea as our
hydrogenation and halogenation.
We just have an extra rule to tell
us which product is the major one.
So we're still gonna be
opening up our doors.
Around our double bond.
So let's highlight the double bond to show
where everything is gonna be happening.
Now with this structure, what we have
to do is we need to count the number
of hydrogens on the right carbon as
well as the one on the left carbon.
So if we are to look closely well
on our structure, If we are to
look on the left hand side, well,
how many hydrogens do you have?
Well, what you have to do is count all
of the bonds that are currently there
and we can see that we have one, two.
So remember, every carbon needs four.
So there are two hydrogens on the left.
One, we're gonna do the same exact
thing on the right hand side.
So when we do that, we are
counting our number of bonds
and we can see that we have.
1, 2, 3, 4, all around this.
So there is zero hydrogens on the right.
So when we open up our doors,
which side is it gonna be going on?
We can see that's going on the
left hand side of our door.
So we are going to redraw
our structure, right?
So we will have that just like, so
we're going to open up both sides.
So we're opening up those doors and
hydrogen is gonna go on the right hand
side with all of the other hydrogens
that are a part of the structure.
But let's show that and maybe in blue
just to kind of show that we have the
two original ones and then chlorine
is going to go on the right hand side.
So hydrogen went with its other hydrogen
friends when we opened the door.
Let's go on to another reaction
type that you're going to see.
The last reaction that we're
gonna come across in addition
reactions is the hydration reaction.
And what you can get is, well,
what is it when you hydrate is
you are adding water, right?
So stay hydrated.
And what happens when you add
water, it creates an alcohol.
Now, with most of these, it typically
happens under an acidic condition.
So very, you're very commonly you'll
see h plus written here, um, maybe
H2SO4, or HNO3, some sort of strong
acid to tell you that we are trying
to create an acidic environment.
So when we're adding water, what
components do you have with it?
Well, it comes down to understanding what
the structure of water is, which is H2O.
Now, if we were to break one of the
bonds of H2O, we can see the two parts.
So let's just say if I
broke the bond right here.
Now with that, we can see that we have
a hydrogen as one part, and then we
also have an OH as our other component.
So we are going to be adding a hydrogen
and an oh, and it's still gonna be
governed by the Markovnikov's rule because
we have two separate different pieces.
So same ideas.
Before we're gonna go through this, we
can mark and draw our double bond, right?
So this is where our doors are
going to be opened in our structure.
We're going to open the bond.
Hydrogen is gonna be added to
the side with more hydrogens.
So let's illustrate our hydrogens.
On the left hand side,
we have two hydrogens.
On the right we have none.
So where is hydrogen gonna go?
It's gonna go on the left
side with more hydrogens.
So when we draw that structure,
we will redraw it again.
We'll draw the same carbons.
But the only difference here is we're
going to be adding one hydrogen to the
left and then our oh group on the right
hand side, creating an alcohol, right?
So we are showing that tertiary
alcohol, um, where it's making tea,
butyl alcohol for our product here.
Uh, let's do some, uh, two more and
just so we can make sure we understand
markovnikov rules and hydration reactions.
Now with this one, it's
the same general idea.
With the first one here, we are going
to be opening up that double bond.
We are adding H and OH while our two
components that are gonna be added.
Now, where do they exactly go?
Well, we have to look at our structure
and count all of our hydrogens.
So if I look at the carbon on the
left hand side, well we can see we
have one, two bonds, three bonds.
So that means there is room for,
there's already, so that means
there's one hydrogen currently here.
Now if I go on the right carbon,
well we can see if we count all of
our bonds, we have 1, 2, 3, 4 bonds.
So that means that
there is zero hydrogens.
On the right hand side.
Okay, let, let me spell out
the word zero 'cause I keep
thinking it looks like an OH.
So we have zero hydrogens on the
right hand side, one on the left.
So when we draw our new structure, when we
open up our double doors, we're going to
be putting one hydrogen with its friend.
So it's just gonna go over here on
the left with its other hydrogen.
Then the oh is gonna go right
in the middle of our chain,
um, away from that hydrogen.
So hydrogen wants to go with more friends.
Now with some structures.
Markovnikov rule does not always apply.
So, for example, with the following
structure, if I count all of my
bonds, I can see that I have one
hydrogen on the left, or sorry, the
top and one hydrogen on the bottom.
So there is not a preference.
It has to be whenever, usually it's
when there's branches involved.
For other functional groups is
when you see that you're gonna have
to add something special to it.
Um, so you always wanna count your
hydrogens to see what's on both sides when
you are going to go for your final result.
So once again, we're gonna open
up those double doors and we're
gonna be adding a H and an OH.
And for this structure, you could draw
either one, um, you could write it where
it's H on the bottom, or OH on top.
Because they're the exact
same structure, right?
You can flip them and
they will be the same.
So they are the same.
Okay?
So both exist.
So it has to depend on really
what type of reaction you have.
Um, with addition, hopefully
this video helped to go through
all the different concepts.
Please check out other videos on
my introductory organic series, and
there's gonna be a lot more to come.
This has been Dr.
Dan.
Thank you so much for watching.
Please hit that like and subscribe button
and I hope to see you all in the future.
Bye now.